<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Architecture on</title><link>https://datasubway.dev/categories/architecture/</link><description>Recent content in Architecture on</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.155.3</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://datasubway.dev/categories/architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Star vs. Snowflake</title><link>https://datasubway.dev/posts/snowflake-vs-start-schema/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datasubway.dev/posts/snowflake-vs-start-schema/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the final installment of our schema series. We’ve seen the &lt;strong&gt;Star Express&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;Snowflake District&lt;/strong&gt;. Now, it’s time for the ultimate showdown. How does Conductor Mickey decide which tracks to lay down for the &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Invisible City&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous posts, we explored two very different ways to organize a subway station:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Star:&lt;/strong&gt; Fast, flat, and simple.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Snowflake:&lt;/strong&gt; Detailed, organized, and space-saving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the real world of Data Engineering, you can’t always have both. You have to choose your priority: &lt;strong&gt;Speed or Storage?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Snowflake Schema: The 'Detailed' District</title><link>https://datasubway.dev/posts/snowflake-schema/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datasubway.dev/posts/snowflake-schema/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;strong&gt;Invisible City&lt;/strong&gt;, as the population grows and the subway map expands, Conductor Mickey sometimes finds that a simple &lt;strong&gt;Star Hub&lt;/strong&gt; isn&amp;rsquo;t enough. When the &amp;ldquo;Station&amp;rdquo; information becomes a giant, messy pile of repeating words, it’s time to move to the &lt;strong&gt;Snowflake Schema&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the Star Schema is the &amp;ldquo;Express Line,&amp;rdquo; the Snowflake is the &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Highly Detailed District.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-a-snowflake-schema"&gt;What is a Snowflake Schema?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous post, we saw how the Star Schema keeps things simple. But what happens when your data starts repeating itself? What if you have 10 million rows, and you’ve written &amp;ldquo;United States&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;North America&amp;rdquo; 10 million times?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Star Schema—The 'Express' Hub</title><link>https://datasubway.dev/posts/star-schema/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datasubway.dev/posts/star-schema/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In our digital subway city, some stations are &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hubs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; They sit right in the middle, and every train line passes through them. In data engineering, if you don&amp;rsquo;t organize your stations, your subway maps will look like a plate of spaghetti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep things clean, we use &lt;strong&gt;Dimensional Modeling&lt;/strong&gt;. The most famous layout for speed is the &lt;strong&gt;Star Schema&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-a-star-schema"&gt;What is a Star Schema?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Star Schema is designed for one thing: &lt;strong&gt;Speed&lt;/strong&gt;. It organizes your data into two distinct types of citizens: &lt;strong&gt;Facts&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Dimensions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Medallion Architecture Journey</title><link>https://datasubway.dev/posts/medallion-architecture-from-mud-to-medals/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datasubway.dev/posts/medallion-architecture-from-mud-to-medals/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;strong&gt;Invisible City&lt;/strong&gt;, the subway doesn&amp;rsquo;t just move people from point A to point B. It moves them through a &lt;strong&gt;refinement process&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When data first arrives at the station, it’s usually messy, tired, and covered in &amp;ldquo;digital mud.&amp;rdquo; We can&amp;rsquo;t let them go straight to the Mayor’s office (the Business Dashboard) looking like that! To fix this, Conductor Mickey uses the &lt;strong&gt;Medallion Architecture&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a three-stage filtration system that turns &amp;ldquo;Raw Junk&amp;rdquo; into &amp;ldquo;Pure Gold.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Time Travel in Azure SQL Database</title><link>https://datasubway.dev/posts/temporal-tables-shadow-station/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datasubway.dev/posts/temporal-tables-shadow-station/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;strong&gt;Invisible City&lt;/strong&gt; subway system, we’ve talked about the &amp;ldquo;Time Machine&amp;rdquo; features in Delta Lake for big data. But what if your main terminal is built on a traditional, reliable foundation like &lt;strong&gt;Azure SQL Database&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, a database has short-term memory. If a passenger changes their destination from &amp;ldquo;Station A&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Station B,&amp;rdquo; the database overwrites the old entry. Station A is gone forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But sometimes, &lt;strong&gt;Conductor Mickey&lt;/strong&gt; needs to know exactly what the city looked like last Tuesday at 2:00 PM. To do that without a magic wand, he uses &lt;strong&gt;Temporal Tables&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Understanding Delta Lake and Delta Tables</title><link>https://datasubway.dev/posts/the-smart-depot-delta-lake/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datasubway.dev/posts/the-smart-depot-delta-lake/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;strong&gt;Invisible City&lt;/strong&gt; subway system, we’ve already upgraded our shipping containers from old wooden crates (CSV) to futuristic, high-tech pods (Parquet). But a depot full of pods is still just a pile of boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a train crashes while unloading, or if two conductors try to move the same crate at once, you get a &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Data Crash.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; To solve this, Conductor Mickey uses a special system: &lt;strong&gt;Delta Lake&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait—is &amp;ldquo;Delta Lake&amp;rdquo; the same as a &amp;ldquo;Delta Table&amp;rdquo;? Let’s clear up the confusion with a trip to the Smart Depot.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Parquet is the Future of Data Shipping</title><link>https://datasubway.dev/posts/parquet-the-flat-pack-container/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datasubway.dev/posts/parquet-the-flat-pack-container/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;strong&gt;Invisible City&lt;/strong&gt;, if the Data Lake is the storage yard, then &lt;strong&gt;Parquet&lt;/strong&gt; is the high-tech, space-saving shipping container we use to pack the goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people are used to CSV files—they are like old-fashioned wooden crates. They work, but they are heavy, take up too much space, and are slow to move. Parquet is the &amp;ldquo;Flat-Pack&amp;rdquo; futuristic alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-vertical-train-why-data-engineers-love-parquet"&gt;The Vertical Train: Why Data Engineers Love Parquet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a subway train full of passengers. Each passenger has a &lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;, an &lt;strong&gt;Age&lt;/strong&gt;, and a &lt;strong&gt;Destination&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Depot, the Terminal, and the Modern Hub: Where Does the Data Live?</title><link>https://datasubway.dev/posts/data-storage-facilities/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://datasubway.dev/posts/data-storage-facilities/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;strong&gt;Invisible City&lt;/strong&gt;, moving data is half the battle. The other half is putting it somewhere. Depending on who you ask—the engineers, the analysts, or the city planners—they’ll give you different answers on where the data should live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s walk through the three main types of &amp;ldquo;storage facilities&amp;rdquo; in our city infrastructure, with &lt;strong&gt;Conductor Mickey&lt;/strong&gt; as our guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="1-the-data-lake-the-massive-storage-yard"&gt;1. The Data Lake: The Massive Storage Yard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Analogy:&lt;/strong&gt; Imagine a giant, sprawling industrial yard at the edge of the city. It&amp;rsquo;s cheap land where we throw everything. Old train seats, crates of unsorted tickets, literal piles of raw iron, and even some lost luggage.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>